If you run an e-commerce brand, and you
don't understand how inventory flows
through your system, you're flying blind
on the thing that matters most.
Inventory is the lifeblood of an
e-commerce business. I've seen brands
with great products, great marketing,
solid margins still run into problems
because of inventory. Huge end-of-year
write-offs, running out of stock without
realizing it, or just calculating the
wrong scaling targets because their
margins were wrong. I'm a fractional CFO
for e-commerce brands, and this is the
module for my e-commerce finance course
that I get the most questions about. I'm
releasing this here because it stands on
its own, and you can get the value out
of this module without watching the rest
of the course. But, understanding this
is how you can finally get a handle on
your inventory, and build a business
that's capable of scaling to nine
figures, rather than one that struggles
at seven figures. So, let's get into it.
All right, this one's going to be a
heavy one. But, I have seen so many
brands, almost all of them, suffer from
not understanding this correctly. So,
it's going to be dense, but if you can
get like 80% of what I'm laying down,
you're going to be better off. So, how
does inventory flow through the system?
Now, the way this looks from brand to
brand can vary a ton. It's actually the
part of working with e-commerce brands
that has the least amount of consistency
because almost everybody's supply chain
is different. There are, however, some
fairly common patterns. So, I'm going to
try to pick something that's about
medium complexity that should apply to
most people watching this. At a minimum,
it'll be very good at explaining the
concepts, even if some of the pieces
aren't super relevant to the way your
supply chain works. So, to try to make
this easy and digestible, we're going to
walk through each step in the inventory
process. We'll also talk about how that
particular step is reflected in the
inventory management system. This is a
system that'll track your inventory
quantities, your values, uh information
about each SKU, expiry dates, locations.
Mind you, the capabilities of an
inventory management system can vary a
lot. A lot of brands don't even have
one. So, I'm going to try to pick a bit
of an average of like what most systems
should be capable of, or even if you're
using a spreadsheet, you should kind of
be tracking. And then, we'll also talk
about what's happening on the accounting
side, so in your accounting software.
Most of the errors that happen with
inventory, in terms of either the
numbers not making sense, or needing to
do a big end-of-year write-off, is
because the steps are not being followed
properly in the various systems. It's
very common for cash to just disappear
into the ether of mysterious inventory,
with nobody really understanding what's
going on, what's there, or why. But, if
you understand how the information
flows, how each step works, and what
each system should be able to say,
depending on its capabilities, you can
be a lot more confident in the data that
you're receiving, and make better
decisions about your business. All
right, so let's get into it. Everything
usually starts with a purchase order.
So, in reality, this is the starting
point of an inventory cycle, when Dave
decides he wants to make a purchase. To
do this, let's say he sends a purchase
order to the supplier of his custom
packaging for the minimum order quantity
of 20,000 units at 50 cents each. So,
what happens in the IMS, or inventory
management system? Most systems should
be able to track that a PO was issued,
but there isn't going to be any sort of
reflection of any increase in quantities
or value in the system, or the total
inventory balance. What happens in the
accounting system? Well, usually, a PO
could also appear there, but a lot of
systems, like a QBO, it's not often
used. So, a lot of times, those POs
don't appear in your accounting
software. If anything, it's more
valuable that it's in the IMS. The next
step is that the supplier requests a
deposit before they begin the
manufacturing run. They send over an
invoice requiring a 50% deposit. So,
Dave pays that, and sends over $5,000.
Some IMSs will reflect this as a
deposit, and tie that amount to the PO
that exists in the system. Other ones
might not, just because, again, there's
no actual physical inventory yet. On the
accounting side, you should see a $5,000
cash outflow, and it should be reflected
as a $5,000 increase to the supplier
deposit GL to track the asset, or the
value that you have, in so far as future
inventory. So, when you pay the deposit,
your deposit in the IMS is going to go
from $0 to $5,000. The status will go
from issued to pending, or whatever they
call it. But, on the accounting side,
your cash balance that you started at
100K, that's going to go to 95K to
reflect the $5,000 that went to the
supplier. And your inventory GL might
have a deposit GL inside that, where the
$5,000 decrease in cash will be
reflected as a $5,000 increase in
deposits. A common error is that a lot
of people just book that $5,000 deposit
directly to an inventory GL. But, this
would immediately cause an error when
you're trying to reconcile between your
IMS and your accounting software,
because there is no inventory. If you
did it this way, in the accounting
system, you're going to see that you
have $5,000 of inventory, but your IMS
shows zero, because you didn't receive
anything. It's just a deposit. So,
tracking those deposits in a separate GL
is a better practice. The next step
would be a pre-shipment payment. So, say
the manufacturer takes a couple of weeks
to actually produce the product. They
send an invoice via email, and ship the
goods. That's due on receipt. So, Dave
sends the remaining $5,000. In some
cases, they might not even ship until
they receive the cash. Now, this is a
little bit of a nuance, but ownership is
usually considered to have transferred
when an item is shipped out. It does
technically depend on the terms, but
it's a fairly common one, so let's just
assume that's the case. So, since the
$5,000 was paid, and the shipment has
been sent out from the manufacturer,
that inventory technically belongs to
Dave. So, the IMS should reflect 20,000
units worth $10,000, but it should be
categorized as goods in transit. So,
it's not at any of the core locations.
On the accounting side, you did have
another $5,000 cash outflow. So, that
$5,000 cash out, the earlier deposit of
$5,000, those should both be moved to a
goods in transit GL. This way, you show
that there are $10,000 worth of goods
that are in transit. They aren't at any
of your locations, and that 10K in the
accounting goods in transit GL should
match the 10K in the IMS that identifies
goods in transit. So, what happens at
this stage is that you added another
$5,000 that you sent to the supplier. It
switched from pending to now being in
transit. And that is reflected in the
accounting system with your cash going
from 95K to 90K, because you sent
another 5,000 to the supplier. Your
deposits are now going to go from 5K to
zero, because what's happening is that
the 10K over here is a combination of
the 5K from deposits, as well as the
other 5K that has been removed from
cash. So, in total, you had 95 here, and
five here, and this is going to go to 90
over here, and 10 here. So, it still all
adds up to 100K on both sides. But,
essentially, the 5K from deposits is now
going into goods in transit. A common
error here is the same as a deposit.
People will take the amount that was
sent to the manufacturer, and put that
directly into inventory. And it's very
common for brands to be able to see
$10,000 worth of inventory on their
accounting software, but then when they
look at their 3PL's inventory listing,
or their IMS, they're like, there is no
inventory, and that mismatch is then
confusing. The next step would be the
freights, the duties, the landed costs.
So, the shipment kind of moves along the
ocean, and arrives to America. Customs
and duties are incurred during the
import process, but a lot of times,
these invoices can be delayed. So, for
the sake of tracking, Dave estimates
that there's going to be a $600 cost
associated to these customs. Many IMSs
will allow for an estimated amount to be
capitalized to the inventory. His system
does, so he capitalized that $600
estimate to the inventory value. So, now
the IMS shows that those 20,000 units
have a cost of 10,000 plus 600, so
10.6K. So, the unit cost has gone now
from 50 cents to 53 cents. On the
accounting side, you haven't actually
sent out any cash yet. So, here, you're
going to have to accrue a liability.
We'll talk about accruals a little bit
later, but the basic idea here is you
know that that's an expense that you've
incurred, even if you haven't received
the bill yet. So, you'll have a GL for
accrued landed costs, which is a
liability, because that's money that you
do have to pay out. And the other side
to that $600 is going to go to your
goods in transit, so that your goods in
transit amount is now going from 10K to
10.6. So, again, the amount in the
accounting software and the IMS match.
So, at this point, we know that we're
going to have $600 of landed cost, or at
least that's our estimate. So, that's
what we're going to track right over
here. Most IMSs will let you track that.
So, that's going to get added to the
$10,000 and change that to a 10,600 over
here. Now, the 10.6 divided by the
20,000 units is going to update the
average cost of 53 cents a unit, instead
of the 50 cents a unit. We haven't
actually paid that $600 in cash, so our
cash is still at 90K in both scenarios,
before and after. However, we're going
to change our goods in transit from the
10K to match this to the 10.6, so that
it matches this over here. And that $600
is going to be sitting in the
liabilities over here, which is an
estimate of a future bill that we're
going to have to receive and pay. A
common error here is that the amount
just isn't estimated, and so the
inventory is going to be undervalued,
which can be fine until you start
selling it, and then selling it at the
wrong COGS. The next step is the receipt
of the inventory into the warehouse or
3PL. So, in reality, the goods are
received into the 3PL. They take it, and
put it on the shelves. On the IMS side,
that 20,000 units is going to move from
goods in transit to a location for the
co-manufacturer. Most IMSs can have
multiple locations, and so you want to
have one where all your raw materials
are stored, another one for your 3PL,
etc. On the accounting side, you're
going to move that 10.6K of value that
was in goods in transit to the relevant
inventory account. In this case, because
it's packaging, we're going to move it
to a raw materials inventory line. Some
might put it to just a single inventory
line, but it's a little bit neater to
kind of have raw materials split out
separately. So, our goods are now
received, so they're going to go from
status in transit to status received.
We're going to put them in the
co-manufacturer's location. We're also
going to keep track of what SKU it is,
which we've been doing the whole time,
but we're trying to keep these charts
simple. In so far as what's happening on
the accounting side, so we're going to
basically take it from goods in transit,
and move that down here, which you can
see over here, to raw materials. That's
pretty much it. At this stage, it's not
uncommon to have to make some
adjustments. In reality, if everything
is received exactly as expected, so you
needed 20,000 units, you got 20,000
units, then fantastic. But, it's not
uncommon to have discrepancies, and so a
common process to be able to identify
those is what we call the three-way
match. So, quick note, this is just one
module from the full e-commerce finance
course that I put together. And it also
covers way more about revenue,
contribution margin, advertising,
profitability, cash flow, etc. You can
learn more about that in the link below.
Anyway, for now, back to inventory
flows. The three-way match involves
comparing the PO to the goods received
document, so keeping track of what we
actually took in, as well as the invoice
from the supplier. If all three of them
match, meaning the PO said, "I ordered
20,000 units." The goods received
document says, "I received 20,000
units." And the invoice says, "I was
charged for 20,000 units." Then,
fantastic. But, if there is a mismatch,
then that often requires a little bit of
investigating. Let's say the goods
received and the invoice don't match the
PO. That could be because I ordered
20,000, but they're only able to fulfill
15,000. So, not ideal, but at the very
least, I'm paying for what I got. It's
good for me to know that though, because
if I needed 20,000 for my whole
inventory forecast to work, I should be
aware that I'm short shipped. On the
flip side, if they shipped more than you
asked and charged you for more than you
asked, you could probably dispute that
and say, "Well, I didn't need 24,000
units." If the goods received doesn't
match the PO or the invoice, then you
have a different issue. They might have
actually shipped you 18K, but they're
charging you 20K, so you don't want to
pay for that extra two. And if they over
shipped you, say 22K, but they're
charging you for 20, then you should be
honest and let them know. If the invoice
doesn't match the other two documents,
then it's a different approach. They may
have overcharged you for what you asked
for and what you received, or they
undercharged you, and again, you should
let them know. Okay, so when
everything's working, your total
quantity in the PO is going to be 20K,
the amount that you received is 20K, and
the amount that they bill you for is
20K. Mind you, they're going to bill you
for the 10,000, this value is 10.6, but
that's because you're adding the 600
that is related to freight, but that's
not going to be coming from the supplier
invoice. Now, let's say your PO is
higher than the amount that is in the
other two documents. You have 15 here
that was received and 15 invoiced. In
this case, they misunderstood your PO or
whatever, and they sent you 15,000, you
actually received 15,000, and they're
going to charge you for less. They're
going to make an adjustment on the IMS
side to just show that you didn't
actually receive 20K. So, simple
adjustment. Same situation, but in the
opposite direction. They invoice you for
the 24, and you received 24, but that
means that you're going to end up having
to pay 12,000 instead of the 10,000 that
you were expecting, so you could dispute
or just take it, and depends on your
relationship with the supplier. Now,
let's say in this case, the PO and the
invoice match, but it's the goods
received document that doesn't. So, you
ordered 20, they are billing you for 20,
but they only shipped 18K. So, obviously
you're not going to pay for 20 when you
received 18. So, in this case, you would
ask them to adjust the invoice, and you
would also adjust the amount in your
system as well to show that it's 18
instead of 20. But, if you'd ordered 20
and they bill you for 10, but you
actually received 22, then you should
probably let them know. So, you'll
update your quantity to show that it's
actually 22,000 units. If you tell them,
then they're going to update their cost
on the invoice, and you're also going to
update your cost accordingly. If you
decide not to tell them, then your costs
would stay the same, and so your unit
cost would be affected because now it is
on 22,000 units instead of 20,000. And
if the invoice is the one that's
mismatched, so you have these two
documents matching, so 20,000 units
ordered, 20,000 units received. If they
bill you for 22,000, then you're
obviously going to let them know because
you don't want to pay 11K instead of
10K. And if they under bill you because
they think they sent you 18, but they
actually sent you the 20, then you would
let them know so that they can bump that
from the nine to the 10. If you decide
not to let them know, then this
basically would go from 10.6 to 9.6,
which would also affect your unit cost.
So, depending on what the issue is, the
adjustment will vary, but this process
usually makes it easy to identify that
there is or isn't a problem. And
sometimes it may require you to make
updates to the IMS and to the accounting
software to match. For example, if on my
PO, I requested the purchase expecting
to be charged 50 cents a unit, but they
ended up charging me 55 cents a unit,
and let's say for whatever reason I
can't dispute that, it's normal, then I
would have to go and update my IMS and
my accounting software accordingly so
that the numbers match up with what
they're actually going to charge me.
Another common issue that's related is
that sometimes what you've received
includes units that were damaged. So,
you order 20,000 units, they ship 20,000
units, and they charge you for 20,000
units. But, let's say at some point when
the warehouse people were receiving it,
they noticed that one box of 100 units
was damaged. So, this will require an
adjustment in the systems. If the amount
is substantial, then you might be able
to go and dispute it with the supplier,
or go through insurance, or talk to the
shipping company. But, oftentimes with
very small amounts, it's just kind of a
cost of doing business that we call
shrinkage. So, for example, if that
happened, we would reduce the quantity
in the IMS by 100 units at 53 cents
each, and on the accounting side, we
would also reduce our raw materials
balance by $53, and put that to the COGS
account called shrinkage. So, you simply
adjust the 20,000 units by 100, so it
bring that down to 19,900. You reduce
the value by 53 cents a unit from 10.6
to 10.547, and that difference is also
reflected on the accounting side, so
your packaging goes from 10.6 to 10.547,
so that these two match, and that
difference in $53 is going to the
shrinkage account right here in COGS.
These types of scenarios are ones where
errors happen very often just because it
is a little bit complex to handle. But,
just having an awareness of it can make
it easier to avoid those issues. The
next step is when he receives the
freight bills. This one can be a little
bit tricky, so I'm going to give you two
scenarios, the easy one and the hard
one. In the easy scenario, the inventory
that he'd received, the 20,000 units,
had had a $600 estimated freight or
customs amount accrued to it. So, we're
going to assume that all that inventory
is still on hand. A bill is then
received from the importer, which ends
up being $200 higher, so 800 instead of
600. On the IMS, you can just adjust
that $600 to $800, and so your inventory
cost would just go up by 1 cent a unit,
for a total of 10.8K instead of 10.6K.
On the inventory side, you'd initially
accrued the $600 as an accrued liability
for estimated future payments, and
booked the $600 to inventory. Now that
you have the actual amount, you would
reverse that estimation, and then book
$800 to accounts payable to pay the
importer, and $800 to inventory. So, you
have 10.8K on the accounting side, too.
All right, so I started off with 20,000
units, the supplier cost was 10K, and I
estimated a $600 of landed gave me a
total of 10.6, and that gives me a unit
cost of 53 cents. Now, what I realized
is that it shouldn't have been $600, it
actually should have been $800. So, in
the IMS, I just update that from 600 to
800. That brings my total cost to
10,800, and so that just changes my unit
cost by 1 cent. On the accounting side,
what happens is that the packaging
amount is still going to get updated to
match the IMS, so it's going to go from
10.6, or like this, I guess, 10.6 to
10.8, but that difference is reflected
over here in the liability. So, I
originally had accrued for $600, which
was my estimated bill. However, now that
I know I actually received 800, what you
basically do is you remove that 600,
reverse it, so that goes to a zero, and
I book the actual $800 that matches what
I was actually sent by the, I don't
know, freight forwarder or whatever, so
that the $200 change from here to here
is balancing with the $200 change from
here to here. But, scenario two is a
little more complicated, but also more
realistic. If everything you'd purchased
is still on hand, then the adjustment is
kind of like I described. In reality
though, oftentimes some of that
inventory has already been sold. So,
let's say for simplicity, half of that
inventory has been sold, and half of it
is still on hand when you get the final
amount related to the freight. Now, many
IMSs can technically go back,
recalculate all of the inventory as well
as the cost of goods for each month in
which the inventory was sold and what's
left over on hand. Essentially, do a
full recalculation of everything with
the updated numbers. But, the problem is
you generally don't want to go back and
start updating your COGS figures on your
accounting records for months that
you've already closed. On the IMS side,
all that really matters is how do you
update what remains, what's still on
hand. So, that part is simple. You would
take the remaining 10,000 units and
increase their cost per unit by 1 cent
each. On the accounting side, it's
slightly more complicated. I'll still
book the $800 of accounts payable for
what I need to pay to the importer, but
a portion of that I'm going to book to
inventory based on what I still have on
hand, and the rest of it I'm just going
to push it through COGS. That's going to
act as catch-up for all the previous
months where we were technically
undercounting our COGS a little bit. So,
we'd initially accrued $600 worth of
freight to the 20,000 units, and there's
10,000 units left, so there's $300, half
of that freight still on the books. So,
when we're reversing the accrual, we're
going to reverse out the $300 and add
the $400 from the half of the $800
accounts payable. And the difference
just goes to COGS as a catch-up. Now,
even if that's confusing, at the end of
the day, the part that matters is that
in the accounting records, what's left
over is $5,400, which matches the $5,400
in the IMS. So, in this scenario, I sold
half of the inventory. So, let's say
before I realized that I needed to
change my landed cost accrual from $600
to the actual 800, I had 10,000 units on
hand, 5,000 supplier cost, cuz that's
half of the 10,000 for 20,000 units, 300
landed cost, because again, that's half
of the 600, which gave me a 5,300 total
unit cost, and so 53 cents per unit.
Now, I realized that I need to take that
from the 600 to the 800, so similarly,
I'm going to be doing that on a half
basis. So, I still have 10,000 units,
still have 5,000 supplier cost, that 300
over here now becomes a $400, so the
5,400 gives me a 54 cent unit cost. On
the accounting side, the inventory is
still going to match the total cost, so
that part makes sense, and I'm also
going to make sure that the inventory
over here matches. So, we're no issues
there. It's really the other portion
that can be a little bit confusing. So,
my accrual went from the 600 to the
actual $800 accounts payable, so that's
a $200 increase. However, half of that
is going to be on the books, so $100 is
why you're seeing the 53 go to a 54. So,
where does the other $100 go? Well, that
is what I'm pushing into the COGS
variance account. This $100 is acting as
a catch-up because it theoretically
should have been expensed in the past
when I sold those other 10,000 units,
but I didn't know, so I'm just catching
up and doing the best I can. This is
definitely a little bit more advanced,
and it can get tricky, but again, it's
just something to be aware of because
this is a place where a lot of mistakes
can happen. When you're making
adjustments or catch-ups or reversing
estimates, there's just a lot of room
for error. But, this same concept or
process applies conceptually to pretty
much any type of adjustment you need to
make. So, for example, same thing if
there was a mistake in terms of the unit
cost you input. You would still have to
do the same sort of adjustment and look
at what's already gone out through COGS,
what sort of catch-up is necessary, and
how do you adjust what you have
remaining on hand. It's just fairly
common for freight cost because those
are very often estimated. So, now let's
say all the raw materials have arrived
at the co-manufacturer, everything is
there. So, the next step would be to
place an order with the co-manufacturer.
Jason sends a PO to the co-man to
prepare an order of 5,000 units of the
elite pre-workout. Several of the steps
are going to go to the beginning of the
flow, so same thing about putting in a
deposit and all that stuff. But, we'll
just jump ahead to the steps that are
new. So, the co-manufacturer receives
their deposit, they get their
pre-shipment payment as well, and they
produce the 5,000 units, which they ship
out. Now, in the IMS, to produce the
5,000 units of finished goods, you have
to have an appropriate reduction in the
amounts of raw materials. So, that might
be 5,000 units of labels, 5,000 units of
packages, and 5,000 units worth of the
weight in the stimulant ingredient. So,
you'll have the reductions in units in
the raw materials, and increase in the
units in the finished goods, and that
will then move to goods in transit,
which eventually then goes into receipt.
On the accounting side, the raw
materials will be reduced based on how
much of it was consumed and what their
accumulated costs were at that point.
And the increase for the final product
would be based on the cost associated
with those raw materials, and that too
would then be recorded to goods in
transit and eventually to finished goods
when it's received. All right, so let's
walk through this slowly. So, to begin,
in our IMS, we have these three
different raw materials: packaging,
labels, and the stimulant ingredient.
And the total value of all of them is
represented over here. So, 10 + 3 +
2,800 gives us a total value in our raw
materials account on the accounting side
of 15,800. So, now we put in a
manufacturing run and we reduce our
packaging by 5,000, so from 20 to 15. We
reduce labels by 5,000 as well, from 15
to 10. And the stimulant is done by
weight, so we had 80 kg and that goes to
70 kg. So, the 7,500, the 2,000, and the
2,100 adds up to the 11,600 of remaining
raw materials. Now, we started off with
zero of the actual good, the Elite
Pre-Workout, but we ended off with 5,000
units. Recall that this 5,000 units is
not only made up from some of our raw
materials, so our packaging, our labels,
and our stimulants, but the
co-manufacturer also adds additional
ingredients and then charges us for
doing all the work. So, let's say the
final cost ends up being the $7.50, so
that 37,500 is reflected right over here
in our finished goods balance. However,
the amount that we actually have to pay
the manufacturer is only for their
ingredients and their work, so that's
33,300.
And that makes sense because if you take
the raw materials of 15,800 and you
subtract 11,600, you get 4,200. And if
you add the 4,200 to the 33,300
that the manufacturer is charging us,
that will add up to the 37,500 right
here. So, in essence, we take the cost
that we incurred in terms of reduction
of our own owned raw materials, and then
also what the manufacturer charges us
for their own efforts as well as their
own ingredients, adds up to that 37,500
of finished goods over here. In some
cases, if the production process is very
long, you can have a work in progress
buffer step. That's to identify why
there might be a reduction in your raw
material, but no associated increase in
finished goods because maybe it just
takes two months to produce a product or
something. But in a lot of cases, that's
not necessary because most manufacturing
processes for most brands is pretty
short. In terms of common errors, it's a
lot of stuff that we've already
discussed, but there can often times be
a little bit of additional shrinkage
that comes from either handling the raw
materials or somebody going and then
noticing that some raw materials were
damaged at some earlier point, or even
wastage with something like the
stimulant ingredient during the
production process. So, they may need to
use 2 kilos to create the 5,000 units,
but they might end up using 2.2 just
because of spillage. You'll also have to
accrue for the shipping costs associated
with moving the finished goods from the
manufacturer to the 3PL, but it's the
same accrual or freight process that
we've already discussed. Another step
that might arise, it really depends on
your supply chain, it might be a bit
nuanced, but I'll share it anyway, is
invoice received is if you receive the
goods but not the invoices. So, for
example, the co-manufacturer sends the
goods, but you haven't received the
invoice associated with the production
process. In the IMS, you're treating it
the same as any other estimate like for
the customs or freight, you're just
going to create an estimate. And you'll
also correct that estimate the same way
we already discussed. On the accounting
side, it's also a very similar process,
except here you'll sometimes use a goods
received not invoiced account. This is
to be able to specifically specify which
inventory is related to finished goods
that you can sell, but you just don't
have the final invoices for yet. It is a
little bit more technically accurate,
but a lot of people just put it to
inventory, and that's understandable,
too. So, this will be very similar to
the accruals from before with landed
cost. So, let's say I have my Elite
Pre-Workout, I received 5,000 units, my
estimate of the cost is going to be
$7.50, so total value is 37,500. The
status is on hand at my warehouse. So,
in my accounting software, I'm going to
show in the goods received not invoiced
account the 37,500 to match this amount
over here, and I'll also have an accrual
of 37,500 because that's what I expect
I'm going to have to pay. But let's say
afterwards, I find out that it was
actually $8 per unit that they were
going to charge me, so my total value is
going to get updated to $40,000 in the
IMS. But now that I have the actual
bill, I'm going to remove the accrual,
so it's going to go to $0 instead of the
37,500, and I'm going to book the actual
bill of $40,000. And then I can also
move the inventory from goods received
not invoiced over to finished goods so
that I have the $40,000 that I actually
do know I owe. Now, while Dave isn't
selling on Amazon yet, some people might
have to ship inventory between different
locations, like sending it to Amazon
FBA. The IMS usually can handle this
pretty well, so you'll have a certain
amount of inventory at your main
location, and then you just identify
which quantity of what inventory you're
going to send over to Amazon FBA or a
secondary location. You can incorporate
a goods in transit step here as well if
there's going to be very long shipping
times. On the accounting side, you don't
actually have to do anything here
because the total finished goods balance
will remain the same regardless of which
locations the inventory split up
amongst. So, let's say you start off
with 5,000 units, so $40,000 of value in
your warehouse, and you have nothing on
hand in Amazon. So, that would show a
finished goods matching amount in over
here in the accounting system of also
$40,000. Then let's say you ship it and
it kind of arrives at Amazon. Nothing
too complicated, basically you ship half
of it, so you have 2,500 at the
warehouse and 2,500 in Amazon, and your
total value is going to be the 20 to the
plus the 20, which is 40, and that's
going to be reflected over here in the
finished goods account on the accounting
side. The accounting side doesn't track
the differences in locations, it just
makes sure that the total inventory that
you have is $40,000. However, that needs
to match up with the totals for all the
locations in the IMS. A common error is
if the IMS cannot handle a goods in
transit while things are in between
locations. What can happen is that if
you are reconciling by pulling the 3PL's
inventory listings, you may in your
system show that you have a certain
amount of units, but the 3PLs don't add
up to that amount. And that's because
it's not factoring in the inventory
that's still in transit. So, it's just
important to be aware of that because
that can sometimes be a reason that you
have a discrepancy, so knowing that
something's still being shipped between
locations, and your if your system can't
track it, at least now you know what the
issue might be. And now we're at the
last step in the inventory flow, which
is reductions. This can happen because
inventory is either lost, stolen,
damaged, or expired. In the IMS, you
simply take the number of units that are
affected by this and reduce it based on
its unit cost. So, if you notice that
100 units were damaged, you reduce your
IMS by 100 units at $0.54 each or
whatever it is. The accounting side is
also fairly straightforward. You'll just
reduce the inventory account by the
relevant amount, whether that be
finished goods or raw materials,
depending on what you're reducing. And
if it was something like being related
to damaged goods, you'll just kind of
push that through the shrinkage COGS
account. This is straightforward, so say
I had 20,000 units at $0.54, which gives
me a value of 10,800, that's going to
match my packaging on hand in my
accounting system. And say I need to
reduce that by 100 units cuz someone
bumped into something, so I'm just going
to reduce in the IMS that 100 units at
the $0.54, which brings me down to
10,746 from the 10,800 over here, and
that will match the change in my
inventory balance in the accounting
system, and that difference in of $54
between the before and after situation
will just go to the shrinkage account
right here. Most business as usual
losses or damages to inventory, that
just goes through COGS. There are in
theory exceptions, like if there's a
dramatic event in a warehouse burns down
or there's some sort of Fast and Furious
heist of a truck where you might not put
that through COGS because you don't want
to mess with your gross margins, and you
can put that as an SG&A expense, but
most of the times COGS works. A lot of
errors will show up because this step
isn't done. So, a lot of times it's just
that the adjustments are not noticed,
nobody realizes that there's inventory
missing or damaged, something might be
reduced from the 3PL, but nobody
communicates that to the company, so
they don't want to make the adjustments
on their end, stuff like that. common
fix for this is just doing periodic
physical counts. So, for example, if you
have 5,000 units per your IMS, and you
do a physical count, and you realize
there's only 4,500 units, then you know
that there's a discrepancy. You might
take steps to identify what caused that
discrepancy or what's going on, but at
the end of the day, you'll probably have
to bring the system to be in line with
the fact that you only have 4,500 units.
Of course, the biggest reduction in
inventory is when you actually sell the
units to the customer, and that's what
we'll be talking about next. So,
hopefully now you understand how
inventory actually flows from a value
and from a physical component
perspective from placing a PO all the
way to being sold. Like I mentioned,
this is just one module, and arguably
one of the hardest ones in the full
e-com finance course. The full course
covers cash flow, advertising
profitability, everything you need to
understand your brand like a CFO. You
can get access to the course if you join
our community, which will also include
access to our dashboarding software,
which we use for our own clients. Plus,
you'll get access to the weekly CFO
office hours with myself. But I hope
that was useful, so subscribe or
whatever, and I'll see you in the next
video.